Hull University Archives: Papers of Robin Page Arnot
Papers of Robin Page Arnot
By Arnot: With GDH Cole, Trade unionism on the railways: its history and problems (London; Labour Research Department, 1917) The politics of oil: an example of imperialist monopoly (London; Labour Publishing Co., 1924) The General Strike, May 1926: its origin and history (London; Labour Research Department, 1926) Twenty years: the policy of the Communist Party of Great Britain from its foundation, July 31st 1920 (London; Lawrence & Wishart, 1940) A history of the Miners Federation of Great Britain (5 vols.) (London; Allen & Unwin, 1949-79) A history of the Scottish miners from earliest times (London; Allen & Unwin, 1955) William Morris: the man and the myth (London; Lawrence & Wishart, 1964) South Wales miners (London; Allen & Unwin, 1967) The impact of the Russian Revolution in Britain (London; Lawrence & Wishart, 1967) About Arnot: Anthony Howe, '"The Past is Ours": The Political Usage of English History by the British Communist Party, and the Role of Dona Torr in the Creation of its Historians' Group, 1930-56' (PhD thesis, University of Sydney, 2004) Antony Howe, ‘Arnot, Robert Page (1890–1986)’, Oxford Dictionary of National Biography, Oxford University Press, 2004 [http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/40281, accessed 30 Nov 2006] A Mason, The General Strike in the North East (Hull; University of Hull Publications, 1970) John Saville, 'Obituary: Robin Page Arnot (1890-1986)', in Bulletin of the Society for the Study of Labour History, vol.51, no.3, 1986, pp1-4
- First Deposit, 1896 - 1978; Hull University Archives; U DAR; U DAR/x1
  U DAR/1 General files, 1896 - 1976
  U DAR/2 Correspondence, 1917 - 1976
  U DAR/3 'A History of the Miners' Federation of Great Britain' (1949- 1979), 1925 - 1976
  U DAR/4 'A History of the Scottish Miners' (1955), 1919 - 1968
  U DAR/5 'A History of the South Wales Miners' Federation' (1967), 1927 - 1973
  U DAR/6 Writings and lectures, 1920 - 1974
  U DAR/7 William Gallacher MP, 1920 - 1965
  U DAR/8 German Democratic Republic, 1948 - 1974
  U DAR/9 Press cuttings, 1930 - 1973
  U DAR/10 Souvenirs, 1953 - 1974
  U DAR/11 Miscellaneous, 1902 - 1978
  - General Files, 1896 - 1976; 59 files; Hull University Archives; U DAR/1; U DAR/x1/1
    - File. Shaw, George Bernard, 1941 - 1972; 1 file; Hull University Archives; U DAR/1/51; U DAR/x1/1/51
      Closed
      - Letter. George Bernard Shaw to Robin Page Arnot: - sending (an article?). Palme Dutt had already asked for it: Typed and signed, 11 Jun 1941; 1 item; Hull University Archives; U DAR/1/51a; U DAR/x1/1/51/a
      - Card from George Bernard Shaw- asking for two proofs: Typed and unsigned, 14 Oct 1942; 1 item; Hull University Archives; U DAR/1/51b; U DAR/x1/1/51/b
      - Letter. George Bernard Shaw to Robin Page Arnot: - Dutt's article on Sidney Webb; comment on 19th century British socialists and politicians (J.S. Mill; William Morris; Hyndman; Asquith; Haldane; Grey; Jevons): Typed: holograph corrections and signed. (4pp.). With 5 typed copies, 5 Nov 1947; 6 items; Hull University Archives; U DAR/1/51c; U DAR/x1/1/51/c
      - Note from George Bernard Shaw - asking for 2 proofs: Holograph, 6 Dec 1948; 1 item; Hull University Archives; U DAR/1/51d; U DAR/x1/1/51/d
      - Postcard. George Bernard Shaw to Robin Page Arnot: - a correction to 'Lysenko article': Holograph, 7 Dec 1948; 1 item; Hull University Archives; U DAR/1/51e; U DAR/x1/1/51/e
      - Letter Robin Page Arnot to George Bernard Shaw - would he put Dutt's article on Sidney Webb, at present in form of a private letter, in form for publication, 11 Nov 1947; 2 items; Hull University Archives; U DAR/1/51f; U DAR/x1/1/51/f
        Returned with holograph note from George Bernard Shaw: - 'impossible: it would damage Dutt...', no date
      - Copies of letters. Robin Page Arnot to George Bernard Shaw. With one draft, 5 Jul 1947-9 Mar 1950; 10 items; Hull University Archives; U DAR/1/51g; U DAR/x1/1/51/g
      - Postcards: F.E. Loewenstein to Editor of 'Labour Monthly', (on cards of George Bernard Shaw): - dealing with an article by G.B.S, 26 Nov-15 Dec 1948; 2 items; Hull University Archives; U DAR/1/51h; U DAR/x1/1/51/h
      - Copy letter: - ('Manager') to George Bernard Shaw: - his note has been sent on to Palme Dutt, who is ill, 31 Dec 1948; 1 item; Hull University Archives; U DAR/1/51i; U DAR/x1/1/51/i
      - Press cutting. Article, 'Front Bench Nonsense',by George Bernard Shaw (from 'Daily Herald'), 13 May 1948; 1 item; Hull University Archives; U DAR/1/51j; U DAR/x1/1/51/j
      - Article, 'The Lysenko Muddle', by George Bernard Shaw. Typescript with holograph additions. (5pp), n.d. [Nov 1948]; 1 item; Hull University Archives; U DAR/1/51k; U DAR/x1/1/51/k
      - Draft lecture, 'Shaw and William Morris', by Robin Page Arnot For a joint meeting of the Shaw Society and the William Morris Society, 11 May - 2 Nov 1956; 2 items; Hull University Archives; U DAR/1/51l; U DAR/x1/1/51/l
        With notes by Robin Page Arnot on Shaw and Morris, 2 November 1956
      - Notes from 'Bernard Shaw, His Life, Work and Friends', by St. John Ervine, 21 Jul 1956; 1 bundle; Hull University Archives; U DAR/1/51m; U DAR/x1/1/51/m
      - 'The Regional'. Vol.2, No.3. Containing satire, 'Shutting up an Individualist', by George Bernard Shaw under pseudonym of Redbarn Wash (from 'Today' (London), n.s. VII. April 1887), Aug 1959; 1 item; Hull University Archives; U DAR/1/51n; U DAR/x1/1/51/n
      - File of Shaw Society papers, 1958 - 1972; 1 file; Hull University Archives; U DAR/1/51o; U DAR/x1/1/51/o
  - 'A history of the Scottish miners' (1955), 1919 - 1968; 4 items, 8 bundles; Hull University Archives; U DAR/4; U DAR/x1/4
    - Correspondence with the National Union of Mineworkers (Scottish Area), 1946 - 1961; 1 bundle; Hull University Archives; U DAR/4/1; U DAR/x1/4/1
    - Draft of Chapter 6 ('From the Sixties to the Eighties'), c. 1950; 1 item; Hull University Archives; U DAR/4/12; U DAR/x1/4/12
  - 'A history of the South Wales Miners' Federation' (1967 - 1973), 1927 - 1973; 25 bundles; Hull University Archives; U DAR/5; U DAR/x1/5
    Related material held at the South Wales Coalfield archive at University College of Swansea
    - Correspondence with Head Office of National Union of Mineworkers, 1957 - 1966; 1 bundle; Hull University Archives; U DAR/5/1; U DAR/x1/5/1
    - Correspondence with National Union of Mineworkers (South Wales Area), 1945 - 1966; 1 bundle; Hull University Archives; U DAR/5/2; U DAR/x1/5/2
  - Writings and lectures, 1920 - 1974; c. 105 items; Hull University Archives; U DAR/6; U DAR/x1/6
    DAR/6/1 - 7 Longer works
    DAR/6/8 - 43 Articles
    DAR/6/44 - 55 Obituaries
    DAR/6/56 - 72 Lectures
    - Projected 'History of the Communist Party of Great Britain', 1957; 1 bundle; Hull University Archives; U DAR/6/1; U DAR/x1/6/1
      Correspondence, minutes, notes and biographical notes. With some original CPGB records, 1920 - 1924
      - Broadsheet. 'Stop the March to Ruin', early 20th cent; 1 item; Hull University Archives; U DAR/6/1a; U DAR/x1/6/1/a
      - Circular letter: holding of Communist Unity Convention on 31 July, 7 Jul 1920; 4 items; Hull University Archives; U DAR/6/1b; U DAR/x1/6/1/b
      - Official Report: Communist Unity Convention of 31 July - 1 August, Sep 1920; 1 item; Hull University Archives; U DAR/6/1c; U DAR/x1/6/1/c
      - Draft Constitution and Rules submitted to Special Rules Conference in Manchester, 23 -24 Apr 1921; 2 items; Hull University Archives; U DAR/6/1d; U DAR/x1/6/1/d
      - Agenda and Resolutions for Policy Conference at St. Pancras Town Hall, 18 - 19 Mar 1922; 1 bundle; Hull University Archives; U DAR/6/1e; U DAR/x1/6/1/e
      - 'The Monthly Record' of the London and Home Counties District Council of CPGB, No. 10, Mar 1922; 1 item; Hull University Archives; U DAR/6/1f; U DAR/x1/6/1/f
      - 'Homes for Workers'. Communist Campaign Leaflet no.3, n.d. [1922]; 1 item; Hull University Archives; U DAR/6/1g; U DAR/x1/6/1/g
      - 'Warning'. Leaflet of National Unemployed Workers' Committee Movement, n.d. [1922]; 1 item; Hull University Archives; U DAR/6/1h; U DAR/x1/6/1/h
      - Press cuttings. Report of policemen found beneath stage at CPGB conference ('Manchester Guardian'; 'Daily News'; 'Daily Herald'), 14 Apr 1924; 3 items; Hull University Archives; U DAR/6/1i; U DAR/x1/6/1/i
      - Statement on Party Organisation, submitted by the Central Executive Committee, 1924; 1 item; Hull University Archives; U DAR/6/1j; U DAR/x1/6/1/j
      - Report of the Control Commission to the Party Congress, 10 May 1924; 1 item; Hull University Archives; U DAR/6/1k; U DAR/x1/6/1/k
      - Report of the Central Executive Committee presented to the National Party Congress, 17 - 19 May 1924; 1 item; Hull University Archives; U DAR/6/1l; U DAR/x1/6/1/l
  - German Democratic Republic, 1948 - 1974; 10 bundles; Hull University Archives; U DAR/8; U DAR/x1/8
    - General correspondence, 1961 - 1963; 1 bundle; Hull University Archives; U DAR/8/1; U DAR/x1/8/1
      Including:
      a) Copy of an article by Robin Page Arnot, 'Economic Crisis (1929 - 1933) and British Coal Mining', and galley - proof of German translation (for publication in 'Geschichtwissenschaft'), 1962
  - Press Cuttings, 1930 - 1973; 22 files; Hull University Archives; U DAR/9; U DAR/x1/9
    - Miscellaneous subject files, 1930; 17 files; Hull University Archives; U DAR/9/1; U DAR/x1/9/1
      a) Africa
      b) Armaments
      c) China
      d) Coal
      e) Cotton
      f) Disputes
      g) Economics
      h) Egypt
      i) Empire
      j) Employments
      k)Fascism
      l)Foreign
      m) Palestine
      n) Railways
      o) Russia
      p) Shipyards
      q) Wood
    - 'Morning Star', containing a series of 3 articles by Robin Page Arnot on the history of May Day, 23 -25 Apr 1973; 1 item; Hull University Archives; U DAR/9/7; U DAR/x1/9/7
- Second Deposit, 1880 - 1979; Hull University Archives; U DAR2; U DAR/x2
  Contents:
  U DAR2/1 Correspondence, 1919 - 1973
  U DAR2/2 Diaries and memoirs, 1967 - 1979
  U DAR2/3 'A history of the Miners'Federation of Great Britain' (1949 - 1979), 1873 - 1961
  U DAR2/4 'A history of the Scottish miners' (1955), 1880 - 1958
  U DAR2/5 'The South Wales Miners: a history of the South Wales Miners'Federation' (1967 - 1973), 1899 - 1972
  U DAR2/6 'William Morris: the man and the myth' (1964), 1885 - 1964
  U DAR2/7 'The impact of the Russian Revolution in Britain' (1967), 1966 - 1967
  U DAR2/8 Other works, 1919 - 1967
  U DAR2/9 Olive E Arnot, 1946 - 1963
  U DAR2/10 Communist Party of Great Britain, 1935 - 1963
  U DAR2/11 Marx Memorial Library and Workers' School, 1843 - 1967
  U DAR2/12 William Morris Society, 1949 - 1970
  U DAR2/13 Miscellaneous, 1891 - 1975
  - Diaries and Memoirs, 1967 - 1979; 36 items; Hull University Archives; U DAR2/2; U DAR/x2/2
    DAR2/2/5-36 are ts. memoirs by Arnot, forwarded to Prof.John Saville and DrJoyce Bellamy, Department of Economic and Social History, University of Hull. The original order of these items has been retained. DAR2/2/8-36 are annotated transcripts of tape recordings.
    - Diary detailing Arnot's visits to Hungary in June and Cyprus in September, 1967; 1 volume; Hull University Archives; U DAR2/2/1; U DAR/x2/2/1
    - Transcript of tape. Webb's Soviet communism: LRD [Labour Research Department]', c. 1978; 2 items; Hull University Archives; U DAR2/2/36; U DAR/x2/2/36
      Part of an original bundle, DAR2/2/5 - 36